Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, the Cold War. It isn't
exactly limited to conflicts with the
Soviet Union. I mean, yes, that is the
definition on paper, but the Cold War
will also cause a lot of things to
happen specifically in America.
Specifically for this video, I want to
talk to you about the Red Scare. But
before that, let's head over to post
World War II Europe. Despite the US's
efforts to contain communism, in 1949,
the Soviet Union gets an atomic bomb.
And also in 1949, China will become
communist. And right after that, in
1950, the Korean War starts. With all
this happening so quickly, fear began to
grow that communism might reach the
United States. And that fear will cause
an era known as the second big Red
Scare, where anti-communist paranoia in
America will lead to blacklisting,
ruined reputations, and widespread
intimidation. And the big person I want
to mention here is a senator named
Joseph McCarthy. And for all you Gen Z
kids, this man is the perfect definition
of a rage baiter. He basically claimed
communists were everywhere in the
government, but often had little to no
evidence to back it up. And I think this
perfectly encapsulates this era. Because
now we see accusations of communism
without any proof, careers being
destroyed left and right as a result,
and all of it really just leading to a
massive public fear. And this will also
lead to serious limits on civil
liberties, especially freedom of speech.
Now, let's give some examples of things
that happened in the Red Scare. Truman's
Executive Order 9835, also known as the
Loyalty Order, investigated government
employees for quote disloyalty and led
to thousands losing their jobs. The
House on Un-American Activities
Committee investigated suspected
communists with a special focus on
Hollywood, where specifically in
Hollywood, 10 writers, directors, and
screenwriters were cited and blacklisted
from the industry. And finally, there
were actual real espionage cases, such
as Alger Hiss, but the more dramatic one
here was probably the Rosenbergs, where
after these two were convicted of
selling secrets to the Soviet Union,
they were executed by electric chair.
But moving on, by the end of the '50s,
pushback against McCarthyism, such as
criticism by Margaret Chase Smith, will
inevitably cause paranoia to die down
and the whole Red Scare by the end of
the '50s will essentially dissipate. But
just remember, even though people argued
about methods, both political parties in
this era agreed that communism must be
stopped. On the screen now are AP-style
questions for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.